Guide to the James Claude Thomson and James C. Thomson Jr. Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
James Claude Thomson and James C. Thomson Jr. Papers
1917-2010
RG 24
Yale University Divinity School Library
9.75
(22 boxes)
The James Claude Thomson and James C. Thomson, Jr. Papers provide a visual and written record of James Claude Thomson's career as a biochemist, professor at the University of Nanking, and medical nutrition expert. The collection contains Thomson's private and professional correspondence, a record of his academic and research work, several copies of his nutritional surveys of Turkey, Iran, and Pakistan, as well as the lectures and speeches he delivered during his long career as a professor. A highlight of the collection is the series of color slides of Iran, Afghanistan, China, Korea, and Japan, and notable film footage of China. Addenda to the original collection also document the life and work of James Claude Thomson's son, James Claude Thomson, Jr. (1931-2002), who was a statesman, historian, and journalist.
Thomson, James Claude, 1889-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Thomson family.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1889 Born in New York. Graduated from Rutgers University and New Brunswick Theological Seminary; received a Ph.D. from Columbia University, and an MPH from Johns Hopkins
1917-1949 Appointed to China by the Presbyterian Board of Foreign Missions. Served as a professor of chemistry, department chairman, then10 years as Dean of the University of Nanking
1933 Published "A study of Chinese wood oils; with special reference to the isolation and the characterization of isomeric eleostearic acids"
1950-1951 Held a Fulbright Professorship at the University of Tehran Medical College
1952 Undertook nutritional survey of Iran
1953-1955 Director of Nutrition Research at the International Christian University in Tokyo
1955-1957 Served as a nutrition consultant for the World Health Organization in Iran, Turkey, and Pakistan
1957-1958 Professor of Nutrition at Yonsei University Medical College, Seoul, Korea
1974 Died in Pennsylvania
Biographical / Historical
1931 Born in Princeton, NJ, son of James C. and Margaret Thomson, Congregational missionaries to China who were in the U.S. temporarily. The family returned to Nanjing, where they were based until 1949. His siblings were Anne (Nancy), Sydney, and John.
1953 B.A. from Yale University
1955 B.A. from University of Cambridge, where he was Yale-Clare Fellow
1959 M.A. from University of Cambridge
1961 Ph.D. in history from Harvard University
1960-1966 Beginning work as aide to Chester Bowles in 1959, JCT, Jr. followed Bowles into the Kennedy administration, serving first as special assistant to the undersecretary of state (1961), then as special assistant to the president's special representative and advisor on African, Asian, and Latin American affairs (1961–63). Under the Johnson administration, Thomson served as special assistant to the assistant secretary of state for Far Eastern affairs (1963–64), and from 1964 to 1966 he was the China specialist on the staff of the National Security Council. In 1966 he resigned in protest over the Vietnam War and returned to Harvard.
1966-1971 Taught at Harvard, published While China Faced West (Harvard University Press, 1969), worked with John K. Fairbank in the field of American-East Asian relations, wrote articles for Atlantic Monthly, etc.
1972-1984 Head of the Nieman Foundation for Journalism at Harvard
1981 Published Sentimental imperialists: the American experience in East Asia / James C. Thomson, Jr., Peter W. Stanley, John Curtis Perry; foreword by John King Fairbank.
1984-1997 Professor of journalism, history, and international relations at Boston University
2002 Died
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence
II. Papers, Reports and Speeches
III. Collected Material
IV. Photographs
V. Slides
VI. Films/Videos
VII Addendum - 2003
VIII Addendum- 2009
James Claude Thomson was an ordained minister, missionary, scientist, and educator. He was Professor of chemistry and later Dean at the University of Nanking from 1917 to 1949. Although he began his career pioneering in the analysis and extraction of Chinese wood oil from the tung-oil nut, he began to feel a deep concern for the hungry and poorly nourished people of Asia. Mid-career, he sought the education and training needed to enter into the fields of public health and nutrition. During his long career as a medical nutrition expert and biochemist, he taught in universities and advised governments in China, Japan, Korea, and the Mideast. Serving as a nutrition consultant for the World Health Organization in the 1950s, he conducted major nutritional surveys of Iran, Pakistan, and Turkey. Though Thomson began his work at the University of Nanking in 1917, the bulk of this collection dates from after 1938.
This collection also contains documentation of the life of James C. Thomson, Jr. who was an educator, statesman, and journalist.
Series I, Correspondence, contains detailed letters written by J. C. Thomson to his wife and family during his separations from them in 1938-1941and 1949 in China, and later in the 1950s when he was on assignment in Iran and Pakistan. When evacuated from Nanking, Thomson went with the University of Nanking to Chengdu, West China and also spent time in Indochina during the war. Correspondence of Thomson written while in the United States primarily relates to travel and employment arrangements. There are several letters from Daniel Dye, whose papers are also held by the Yale Divinity Library (Record Group No. 22). Additional correspondence of Thomson from the period when he was at the University of Nanking is available in the Archives of the United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia, YDL Record Group No. 11.
Series II, Papers, Reports and Speeches, primarily contains material written by Thomson on nutrition and health-related subjects. Series III, Collected Material, includes writings on similar subjects by others, as well as miscellaneous material relating to the Thomsons' travels, and an obituary of Thomson.
Series IV, Photographs, Series V, Slides, and Series VI, Films, contain high quality visual documentation of the areas where Thomson lived and worked. The photographs and slides are individually identified to a large exent. Video use copies of many of the films have been made and are located in the last box of the collection.
Two addendums added to the collection in 2003 and 2009 provide additional documentation of James Claude Thomson, and of his son James Claude Thomson, Jr.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Papers, Reports and Speeches
III. Collected Material
IV. Photographs
V. Slides
VI. Films/Videos
VII Addendum - 2003
VIII Addendum - 2009
Sino-Japanese War, 1894-1895; Missions -- China; Missions; Nutrition -- Middle East; Educators; Missionaries; Thomson, James Claude, 1889-; Thomson, James Claude, 1931-; Jinling da xue; World Health Organization
- Correspondence, 1917-1918 May; Series I
  - James Claude Thomson (JCT) to parents from Shanghai, Nanking, 1917-1918 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - JCT to parents from Nanking, Kuling, 1918 June-1919 Aug (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  - JCT to parents from Nanking, Peking, 1920-1923 (Box 1, Folder 1b)
  - JCT to John Allison, American Embassy in Nanking re. incident at Japanese embassy, JCT report re. Univ. of Nanking Hospital, 1938 Jan- June (Box 1, Folder 1C)
  - JCT to family from Chengtu, Indochina, Kunming, Shanghai, 1939 Jan -Dec 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - JCT to family from Haiphong, Indochina, 1940 Jan (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - JCT to family from Haiphong, Indochina, 1940 Feb (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - JCT to family from Indochina, Kunming, 1940 Mar - 1941 May (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - JCT in NY incl. to C.A. Evans, Associated Boards for Christian Colleges in China re. transportation of college supplies, and from Daniel Dye, June 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - JCT in U.S. incl. to/from Daniel Dye, 1941 Jul (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - JCT in U.S. incl. to/from C.A. Evans, Daniel Dye, 1941 Aug (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - JCT in U.S. incl. to/from Daniel Dye, chemical supplies company, Y. G. Chen (President of University of Nanking in Chengtu), 1941 Sep-Oct (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - JCT in U.S. incl. to/from Daniel Dye, Y. G. Chen, Elsie Priest, chemical supplies company, 1941 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - JCT in U.S. incl. to/from chemical supplies co., Y. G. Chen, 1942 Jan (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - JCT in U.S. incl. to Elsie Priest, Y. G. Chen, 1942 Feb-Mar (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - C. A. Evans to JCT, incl. memo from M. C. Swen re. preparation of photographic emulsions in China with photographic samples, 1942 Mar 4 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Incl. from C.A. to JCT in U.S. re. shipment of materials to China, 1942 Apr (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - lncl. to Y. G. Chen, 1942 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Incl. to Y. G. Chen, 1943 Jan, Mar (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Re. insurance and financial matters, re. monetary gift to JCT, 1944 Apr-Oct, Nov 1948 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Incl. from JCT in Hong Kong re. shipment of materials during period teaching in Canton, 1947 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - JCT to family from Kunming, 1949 Aug (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Incl. JCT to family from West China, 1949 Sep (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Incl. from China, re. shipment of luggage, JCT to family from Iran, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Incl. re. JCT's nutritional assessment survey in Iran, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Re. JCT's work as Director of Nutrition Research at International Christian University, Tokyo, Japan, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Incl. to JCT in Japan from wife, incl. re. shipment of luggage, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Incl. arrangements for Iran project, 1955 Jul-Oct (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Re. work of JCT in Middle East, 1955 Nov (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Incl. JCT to family from Tehran, 1955 Dec (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Incl. JCT to family from Tehran, 1956 Jan 3-17 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Incl. JCT to family from Karachi, Pakistan and re. JCT work in Pakistan, 1956 Feb 1-11 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Incl. JCT to family from Karachi, reports re. work, 1956 Feb 12-29 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Incl. JCT to family from Karachi, incl. re. WHO assignment in Turkey, 1956 Mar-May (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Re. arrangements for assignment in Turkey, 1956 Jun- Aug (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Re. assignment in Turkey, 1956 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Re. reports on work in Middle East, arrangement for Presbyterian Board assignment as Professor of Nutrition at Yonsei University Medical College, Seoul, Korea, 1957 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Re. arrangements for travel to Japan and Korea, 1957 Jul -Aug (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Re. arrangements for travel to Japan and Korea, 1957 Sep (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Re. personal effects stored in Shanghai, 1958 Feb - Jul (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Incl. re. disposition of personal effects stored in Shanghai, 1958 Aug -Dec (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Re. disposition of personal effects stored in Shanghai, 1959 Apr to Nov (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Re. disposition of personal effects stored in Shanghai, kodachromes, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - JCT to "Mohammed", JCT to family, Christmas card, letters re. JCT's career, misc. JCT correspondence, MT to N. Thurber, 1961-1974 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Papers, Reports and Speeches, 1918 May; Series II
  Scope and Contents
  These materials are by James Claude Thomson. See the Addendum for writings and speeches by James Claude Thomson, Jr.
  - Article reprinted from the Journal of the American Chemical Society, entitled "The Action of Thionyl and Sulfuryl Chlorides on Sulfur and Phosphorus", 1918 May (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Thomson's dissertation for Columbia University, entitled "A Study of Chinese Wood Oils", 1933 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Article reprinted from the Journal of the American Chemical Society, entitled "A Spectroscopic Study of Eleostearic Acids from Chinese Wood Oil", 1934 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Article in Nutrition Reviews, entitled "The Food Problems of Free China", 1943 Jul (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - University of Nanking Nutrition Project:: diet record summary and calculations, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - University of Nanking Nutrition Project:: diet records, 1948 Jun 20-26 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - University of Nanking Nutrition Project: diet records, 1948 Oct 31-Nov 6 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - University of Nanking Nutrition Tables (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Typed copy of "The Food Problems of Free China" on loose-leaf paper (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Report of work with children from Chengtu orphanage, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 53A)
  - Report for the United Nations World Health Organization on "Nutrition in Iran", 1952 Oct (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Draft of report for the United Nations World Health Organization on "Nutrition in Iran" (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Typescript reports re. Iran (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Nutritional Status Surveys from the Ministry of Health of Iran, copies in English and Persian (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - FAO-WHO report on Nutrition in Turkey, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Nutrition in Turkey report continued, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Nutrition in Turkey report continued, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Nutrition in Turkey report continued, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Nutrition in Turkey: Report on a Nutritional Status Assessment Survey of 3288 Schoolchildren, 1956 Nov-Dec 1956 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Nutrition in Turkey: Schoolchildren report cont., 1956 Nov-Dec (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Nutrition in Turkey Report: a copy with corrections, 1956 Nov-Dec (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Nutrition in Turkey Report (copy with corrections) and notes, 1956 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Nutrition in Turkey: Schoolchildren report, additional copy, 1956 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Nutrition in Turkey: Schoolchildren report cont., 1956 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Personal notes of J.C. Thomson taken in preparation for the FAO-WHO Turkey Nutrition Report, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Nutrition in Pakistan report: a supplement to the joint FAO/WHO/UNICEF Pakistan Milk Survey, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Nutrition in Iran II: WHO report, 1957 Mar (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Clinical and Medical Nutrition, Vol. 1, Lecture 1, "Medical Nutrition" (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Clinical and Medical Nutrition, Vol. 1, Lectures, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Clinical and Medical Nutrition, Vol. 1, "Malnutrition" (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Clinical and Medical Nutrition, Vol. 1, "An Adequate Diet: Its Criteria and How to Obtain it." (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Clinical and Medical Nutrition, Vol. 1, "The Vitamins" (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Clinical and Medical Nutrition, Vol. 1 "Thiamine and Malnutrition" (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Clinical and Medical Nutrition, Vol. 1 "Riboflavin" (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Clinical and Medical Nutrition, Vol. 1 "Niacin and Pellagra" (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Clinical Nutrition, Vol. 2, "Food Prescription in Nutrition", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Clinical Nutrition, Vol. 2, "Hospital Diets", 1957 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Clinical Nutrition, Vol. 2, "Nutrition in the Care of the Surgical Patient", 1957 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Clinical Nutrition, Vol. 2, "Protein Nutrition in Pediatrics", 1957 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Clinical Nutrition, Vol. 2, "The Importance of Water and Hormones", 1957 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Clinical Nutrition, Vol. 2, "Folic Acid", 1957 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Clinical Nutrition, Vol. 2, "Vitamins" (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Clinical Nutrition, Vol. 2 "Thiamine and Tubefeeding", 1957 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Clinical Nutrition, Vol. 2 "Pellagra", 1957 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Clinical Nutrition, Vol. 2 "Riboflavin and Folic Acid", 1957 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Clinical Nutrition, Vol. 2 "Anemias" (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Clinical Nutrition, Vol. 2 "B-12 Vitamin and other B-Vitamins" (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Clinical Nutrition, Vol. 2 "Vitamin K, Vitamin E, and Misc." (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Syllabus for Medical Nutrition, Yonsei University Medical School, Seoul, Korea, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Syllabus for Medical Nutrition, Yonsei University Medical School, Seoul, Korea, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Syllabus for Medical Nutrition, Yonsei University Medical School, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Syllabus for Medical Nutrition, Yonsei University Medical School, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Syllabus for Medical Nutrition, Yonsei University Medical School, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Syllabus for Medical Nutrition, Yonsei University Medical School, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Syllabus for Medical Nutrition, Yonsei University Medical School, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Syllabus for Medical Nutrition, Yonsei University Medical School, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Nutritional Status Surveys, Yonsei University Medical School (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - FAO-WHO Report on Turkey in Turkish, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Outlines and notes from articles on nutrition in China, 1923-1935 (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Outlines and notes from articles on nutrition in China, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - Outlines and notes from articles on nutrition in China, 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 105)
  - Outlines and notes from articles on nutrition in China, 1940-1945 (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Notes, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - Notes regarding nutrition in China (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, Lecture #1, "Clinical Nutrition: Some Recent Advances in the Science of Human Nutrition" (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, Lecture #2, "The Modern Concept of Malnutrition" (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, Lecture 3A "An Adequate Diet: How Can It Be Obtained" (Box 4, Folder 111)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, "The Vitamins and Avitaminosis A" (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, Lecture 5A, "Thiamine and Athiaminosis and the Berberis" (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, Lecture 5B, "Riboflavin, B2" (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, Lecture #6 "Niacin, Amounosis and Pellagra" (Box 4, Folder 115)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, Lecture #8 "Ascorbic Acid, Scurvy and Avitaminosis C" (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, Lecture 8B, "Pyridoxine (The Vitamin B6 group)" (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, Lecture 8C, "Folic Acid" (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, Lecture #9, "Iron, B-12" (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, Lecture 9B, "Protein Deficiency" (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, Lecture #11, "Diagnosis of Nutritional Deficiency" (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, Lecture #12, "The Role of Proteins in Hormone Metabolism" (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Speech, "Some Recent Advances and Trends in Nutrition", 1945 Sep 31 (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - Speech, "Our Food and Our Health" (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - Speech, "Foods, Vitamins and Our Health", 1946 Dec 3 (Box 4, Folder 125)
  - Speech, "Our Food and Our Health" at Okaba-Mura, 1953 Sep 11 (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - Speech, "Nutrition in China", 1950 May 11 (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - Speech, "The Modern Concept of Nutritional Deficiency Diseases" (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Speech, "Can the Modern Knowledge of Food and Nutrition Build a Healthier People?" (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - List of Diseases, Department of Medicine, United Hospital Chengtu (Box 4, Folder 130)
  - Speech, "Some Recent Important Contributions of Chemistry to the Field of Food and Nutrition" (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - Speeches, "Vitamins in Health," and "Recent Advances in Nutrition"notes (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Speech, "Changing China and the Chinese Christians" (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - Speech, "A Short Talk on Food and Health for Mothers and Teachers" held in Canton, China, 1949 Jun 18 (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Speech, "Vitamins and Health" (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - Speeches, "The Influence of Milling, Preserving and Cooking on Food Values" and "Calcium and Phosphorus Requirements" (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Speech, "Mineral Elements in Nutrition," related notes (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - Medical Nutrition Lectures, 1950-1959 (Box 4, Folder 138)
- Collected Material, Dec 1938; Series III
  - "Chinese Method of Infant Feeding and Nursing" by B.S. Platt and S.Y. Gin, Dec 1938 (Box 5, Folder 139)
  - "A Student Church in Kunming," article in The Chinese Reporter, Feb 1940 (Box 5, Folder 140)
  - "A Study of the Woburn Iodine Absorption Method" by J.D. von Mikusch and Charles Frazier, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 141)
  - University of Nanking newsletter, July 1944 (Box 5, Folder 142)
  - University of Nanking - Bulletin No. 13: Report of the President and the Treasurer, 1922-1923 (Box 5, Folder 142a)
  - University of Nanking - Bulletin No. 3: Report of the President and the Treasurer, 1924-1925 (Box 5, Folder 142b)
  - University of Nanking - Bulletin No. 7: Report of the President and the Treasurer, 1925-1926 (Box 5, Folder 142c)
  - University of Nanking - Thirteenth Annual Report of the College of Agriculture and Forestry, 1926-1927 (Box 5, Folder 142)
  - University of Nanking - Officers of Administration and Instruction, 1924-1925, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 142e)
  - "Some Demographic and Health Characteristics of 173 Villages in a Rural Area of Iran," by M.B. Mashayekhi and Guy S. Hayes, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 143)
  - "Some Demographic..." cont., 1952 (Box 5, Folder 144)
  - "Some Demographic..." cont., 1952 (Box 5, Folder 145)
  - "Some Demographic..."cont., 1952 (Box 5, Folder 146)
  - Political map of Pakistan, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 147)
  - World Food Congress Commission Health in Relation to Nutrition and Working Efficiency in Turkey by Iskender Bayka, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 148)
  - Tourist information about Kashmir (Box 5, Folder 149)
  - Media Area Retired Men's Association; Old Guard Retirement Club, 1963,1966 (Box 5, Folder 150)
  - Obituary of JCT (1974); Biographical information; Visas and travel passes, 1964-1974, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 151)
  - Public statement re. Nanking incident March 24, 1927 - signed by A. J. Bowen, P. F. Price, Donald W. Richardson, W. R. Williams, C.A. Mattis, John H. Reisner, J. C. Thomson, C. Stanley Smith, Harry Clemons, G.W. Loos, Jr., L. J. Owen, Edwin Marx, L. B. Ridgely, W. F. Robert, J. G. Magee, C. L. Pickens, Jr., N. D. Gifford, Jr. (Box 5, Folder 151a)
  - Miscellaneous collected material (Box 5, Folder 151b)
- Photographs, 1951; Series IV
  - Two prints of a caravan in Iran, one print of J.C. Thomson with women and a child in Nahmatabad, Iran, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 152)
  - One print of a Tehran classroom (the Rahnama High School) with an American Fulbright teacher; one print of a Fulbright teacher conducting a class on agriculture at the Near East Foundation near Tehran; one print of students of the rural teacher-training school near Tehran learning how to work manure into the soil for proper fertilizing (Box 5, Folder 153)
  - Print of J.C. Thomson examining a little girl during a health tour of Nahmatabad, Iran; print of a boy taken in Vahnabad; one print of women weaving; J.C. Thomson and Iranian counterparts (Box 5, Folder 154)
  - Print of J.C. Thomson with Dr. Hachiro Yuasa, president of the International Christian University, and Dr. Iwao Ayusawa, faculty member greeting Thomson at Haneda Airport near Tokyo; print of J.C. Thomson shaking hands with Dr. Yuasa; print of an eye examination given to a co-ed of the ICU College of Liberal Arts by J.C. Thomson; print of Thomson, Dr. Stanley I. Stuber, and Russell L. Dirgin; print of ICU faculty members during a conference of the ICU Foundation in New York (Box 5, Folder 155)
- Slides, 1948-1949; 1949; Series V
  - China Slides: slide carousel #5, slides of Nanking, Kuling, Canton, Hong Kong and Macao; slide carousel #6, slides of Yunnan and Sikang, incl. leprosy colony, market scenes, Lolo country, Nosu people, 1948-1949; 1949 (Box 6, Folder 156)